Rym: It's Wednesday, December 20th, 2023, I'm Rym, I'm Scott, and this is GeekNights.
Rym: Tonight, we are reviewing Hayao Miyazaki's third final film, The Boy and the Heron.
Scott: Let's do this.
Scott: So continuing the trend of not forgetting the past so that we don't run out of opening bits, let's go back to, I mean, I was in California for a whole week, right, but let's, you know, other stuff happened there, you know, we had a Thanksgiving there and stuff, right, but none of it was particularly noteworthy, but I do want to comment on LAX, the airport.
Rym: I think it's my third most hated airport on earth as someone who has flown literally around the world in a single trip once.
Scott: Yeah, so I didn't realize this, like when we got there, right, you know, we had relatives coming to pick us up at the airport, right, who lived there, who were going to sea, and we go outside and we stand, it's pretty typical, there's two lanes, right, there's the lane where all the, you know, buses and shuttles and things come through, right, and you can, and then there's a, you go, you cross the street and then you wait there and you just, you look up, there's like some number like, oh, hey, we're waiting at 5D, come get us, right, you know, when you, at terminal X, whatever.
Rym: I realize I've never been outside at LAX, I've only ever used LAX to transfer to another flight in my entire life.
Scott: Yes, I mean, this is only the first time I had been there outside, right, the only other time I was in California in my life was at LAX, transfer to a plane to Australia, so that was it, so standing outside, palm trees, it's warm, at least warm for the time of year, not too bad, right, seems good, and we stand there waiting, and we had to wait quite a while before
Rym: the car
Scott: comes to get us, right, they were waiting in like, you know, the cell phone lot, like you do, right.
Scott: Now,
Rym: on one hand, I'm thinking, you know, actually, I think two things here, on one hand, I think it's car town, you'd think the cars would like come a lot, but then I think it's car town, is there just insane traffic, which LA might be as a city, let's just say, famous for.
Scott: Well, you might be, you know, that's if you're, you know, an issue, if you're talking about just LA, California in general, it's particularly the LA area, right, but no, there is an issue particular to LAX, and it being incredibly stupid and poorly designed, even if you're accepting car dominance, right, and not addressing that larger issue.
Rym: The rare above and beyond.
Scott: Yes, the rare above and beyond.
Scott: Wait, LAX only has four roadways?
Rym: There's a lot bad about LAX the more I'm looking.
Scott: So I did not realize this until I didn't think about it too much.
Scott: I was like, oh, we had to wait a while for them to come get us, and they got us, and we went, we left, right.
Scott: But when we went back to LAX to go home, I was in the car, right, trying to get to a departures zone, right, which I had not experienced.
Scott: I had only experienced being picked up at arrivals and leaving, and so we're doing this late at night, right, because we had like a red eye that took off at like one a.m.
Scott: or whatever, something like that.
Scott: So we're coming in at like nine or ten at night or something, and we're at terminal five, I think.
Scott: I think it was five.
Scott: It was it wasn't a low number.
Scott: And so with the road in LAX is an oval kind of road, not really an oval.
Scott: It's more like straight and then a two turns and then straight back like a like a loop.
Scott: Right.
Scott: But like a more like a, you know, not a hairpin because you're not.
Scott: you know, it's not that tight, but you get the idea.
Scott: And so we're going in and we're driving on this road and it's not moving basically at all.
Scott: And I can see this terminal one there.
Scott: Right.
Scott: And it's like, OK, well, we're not going to terminal one.
Scott: Like, just keep going.
Scott: It's like, well, we can't keep going because the road doesn't have like turn offs for the terminals.
Rym: Wait, I've never seen an airport that was bigger than like one of like one of those tiny Michigan airports, like a JFK airport.
Scott: You can go and like if you actually just go to JFK and you're not going to any terminal, you can just drive in a big loop and not go to any departures or arrivals and then leave.
Rym: You get off the freeway to get on an airport freeway that literally has exits like here's the exit for terminal one.
Rym: Here's the exit.
Rym: Exactly.
Scott: So if you're not going to terminals one, two, three, you just pass right by them and you go to the off ramp for terminal four.
Scott: And so is it possible that there's so many people going to the airport that it gets backed up?
Scott: It's like it can happen, but it's pretty rare.
Scott: Yeah.
Scott: Right.
Scott: You only really have to wait once you get off the ramp and then you're waiting, you know, at the terminal, basically.
Scott: But here everyone is going to a high numbered terminal is stuck waiting behind everyone at the low numbered terminals until they can squeak past and get to the next.
Rym: And so and it's basically just this block of non-moving cars that is terrifying, considering it is the fourth busiest airport in the world.
Scott: And it's even worse.
Scott: Imagine if you went there and you drop someone off at terminal one and now to leave, you have to basically sit behind everyone at terminals two, three, four until you can get to the exit all the way at the other end.
Scott: There isn't like a quick escape path of any kind.
Rym: If only there were an invention, like some sort of car, but it went on rails and it wasn't stuck at the point.
Scott: we're not addressing the larger issue.
Scott: Right.
Scott: We're saying that, like, I think, you know, otherwise other than that, you know, I think that is like really the biggest wrong thing.
Scott: I didn't notice anything else at the airport that was particularly awful compared to other airports.
Scott: Other than that, that was like by far the standout, complete garbage design problem that I've never seen any other airport big or small so foolishly constructed.
Rym: It's extra funny because when you first told me this story, I had like my mom had just come and visited us in New York.
Rym: So I got to drive through for the first time the brand new LaGuardia, like the completely redesigned one.
Rym: And it like goes above and beyond to make sure traffic, car traffic cannot get backed up in there is in and out as fast as possible.
Rym: It's got like follow this color and you will get to this destination like signage everywhere.
Rym: It's actually kind of amazing.
Scott: You know, the new LaGuardia is fine.
Scott: The terminals are nice in the inside.
Rym: I just wish it flew anywhere I go.
Scott: There are only three problems with LaGuardia Airport.
Rym: Literally, there's only one problem I can say.
Rym: Nowhere I ever fly has a flight that leaves from LaGuardia.
Scott: Well, no, they're a place I could have places I go.
Scott: Like the problem is that flights often don't take off there or have problems.
Scott: Right.
Scott: Two, they don't have to put a city bike dock in the airport or any kind of secure bicycle park.
Scott: It's close enough.
Scott: I could buy.
Rym: Yeah, I mean, I have walked home from flights at the airport before.
Scott: There are city bike docks just outside of the airport.
Scott: It's like you really just can't throw one dock in there somewhere.
Scott: There's so much parking lot.
Scott: It just like throw one in with like, what, you know, 20 bikes.
Rym: It's like I would literally put my backpack on and take a city bike to that airport and fly.
Rym: It would be amazing.
Scott: Exactly.
Scott: It's.
Scott: and the third problem with LaGuardia Airport is that obviously the only public transportation that goes there is the bus, which is fine for me because the bus that does that, is it a convenient?
Rym: last time I tried to use that bus?
Rym: It's in a pretty good spot over here, too.
Rym: But my experience was I go to the bus stop, you know, I'm paranoid.
Rym: I get to airports like way earlier than I probably need to.
Rym: So I'm waiting for the bus.
Rym: The bus comes and it's already completely full and then it just leaves and then another bus comes and it's also just completely full and then it leaves.
Rym: And then I call the cab.
Scott: No, I never had that problem.
Rym: I had that happen and Emily had it happen, but that was a long time ago now.
Rym: I just take cabs to that airport, though, because it's like a 15 minute cab ride, honestly.
Scott: I just don't use a car if it's not necessary.
Scott: And the bus is fine.
Scott: Yeah.
Scott: Anyway, but there should be a train that goes to that airport.
Rym: There should.
Scott: But why not a ferry?
Scott: Why not a ferry, too?
Rym: Which is funny, too, because like all the people I have known in my life who ended up in L.A.
Rym: don't never seem super happy about
Rym: L.A.,
Rym: like they had to go there for some reason, but it just doesn't seem like it's a great place to live compared to New York.
Scott: And I'm saying, well, I mean, you know, what I thought of it before ever going there in my life.
Scott: Right.
Rym: Well, you probably imagine a 16 lane highway and that's it.
Scott: I mean, I mean, Chicago actually had the scarier highway.
Rym: I know exactly what highway you're talking about, too.
Rym: I grew up out there.
Scott: But there's, you know, but
Scott: L.A.,
Scott: it has, you know, positive aspects.
Scott: Right.
Scott: But, yeah, I wouldn't live there.
Rym: Yeah, absolutely not.
Scott: I would trade for the weather, though, you know.
Rym: Oh, yeah.
Rym: If you could have a New York City with L.A.
Rym: weather, but then already we're talking magic.
Rym: So I want a New York City with like Galapagos weather, which is just a lot of Asian cities.
Rym: And you have other problems anyway.
Rym: So instead of news, I got a little geek bite here because Hilda, the absolutely phenomenal animated series on Netflix that is based on the comics, which are apparently good.
Rym: I've never actually read them by Luke Pearson.
Rym: Hilda's just great.
Rym: I've talked about it on the GeekNights before, but it's not super long.
Rym: So the final season of three of the animated series, which covers, as best I can tell, all of the comics, the comic itself being complete, is now on Netflix.
Rym: So if you want to watch Hilda, literally all of it is just on Netflix and there isn't even that much of it.
Rym: So season three seems like it wraps up whatever long form plot threads there might be in our otherwise largely episodic, charming, indie comic feeling animated series.
Rym: But having watched a few episodes of season three, we're pretty much just powered through to the end.
Rym: And I recommend that all humans watch Hilda if they have the capacity to do so.
Rym: And if Scott ever watches it, we will do a show on it.
Rym: If not, at some point, I'll just randomly do a show with Emily if we have to skip a show because one of us is out of town for GeekNights stuff generally.
Scott: Seems unlikely because that's not even in the queue and the queue's already large.
Rym: I mean, this this comic is the kind of thing that you would just read and really try to get me to read to do a show on.
Rym: But they happen to have made one of the better animated TV shows I've seen based on it.
Rym: Anyway, the things of the day.
Rym: So this thing is called Punch Punch Forever, and it was uploaded by a YouTube account called Speedoroo, which has a Patreon that's just called like Speedo.
Rym: And I couldn't find a ton of info with cursory investigation into this person's deal other than they seem to just make funny animations and their Patreon has a warning that there is, quote, NSFW stuff if you go above the five dollar tier.
Rym: I didn't look into what that is.
Rym: But this video standalone is eight minutes long.
Rym: And imagine one of those old anime like Dragon Half.
Rym: Now, imagine if someone just made a brand new show animated almost more in an American style, like almost more like a Powerpuff Girls, like a modern American style, but drawn and filtered in a way to look like it was made in the era with the tools that a show like Dragon Half was made.
Rym: And imagine that it is like funny, deep parody of all the kinds of anime that are like that with those kinds of tournaments and nonsense and that kind of humor just all crammed into this like it's a legit anime episode, basically.
Rym: I don't know.
Rym: I don't want to even just watch it.
Rym: There's a lot going on here.
Rym: And I think other people need to see this before I have a lot to say about it.
Scott: So, yeah, I mean, the aesthetic of this thing is really something.
Scott: And also, I think it's been quite a while since we've, you know, like I've seen an original like, you know, free Internet animation like what those the right.
Rym: I see a lot of shorter ones, but I guess what stands out is that it's funny.
Rym: But a lot of times things like this tend to be either the joke overstays is welcome.
Rym: They only really have one joke.
Rym: Like it's it's kind of just tedious.
Scott: Every time this feels like a Studio Trigger had like Inferno Cop and Turning Girls.
Scott: Right.
Scott: And then you had.
Rym: There were some others, but the production values on this are really high.
Scott: Senpai Club was one.
Rym: But every time this feels like it's about to overstay, it's welcome.
Rym: It either escalates, swerves or literally just fast forwards to the next thing.
Rym: That'll be funny.
Rym: Yeah.
Scott: I think I need to get YouTube to recommend me the people out there who are making these sorts of things.
Rym: So YouTube recommended this to me recently.
Rym: That's how I found it.
Rym: And I think it's because Emily and I have both been watching a lot of independent animation lately on.
Scott: I just I'll just watch this channel and hopefully YouTube will sort itself out.
Rym: Yeah.
Rym: Between this and watching there's all those animation memes where like kids who are into making art are making like six second animation loops that then they do effects on and put over a song loop.
Rym: That's been like a thing for several years now.
Rym: Watching a lot of those seem to be what brought me specifically to have this recommended to me.
Rym: All right.
Scott: So when I was a kid in the days before Game Boys.
Scott: Right.
Scott: And maybe even in those days, I would do a lot of puzzles.
Scott: You know, you do some puzzles like the mini page in the newspaper.
Scott: There would be like, you know, word searches and find the difference and find the hidden thing.
Rym: Turn it upside down to figure out what the fox detective has to say about the situation in the image.
Scott: Exactly.
Scott: You had.
Scott: I also would also get these.
Scott: I think they still make them these yes and no books like yes and no K and O W where you'd have an invisible ink pen and you would each page of the book had like a different puzzle that you would.
Rym: I remember something like that being for sale in the Scholastic Book Club at some point.
Scott: Yeah, Scholastic Book Club also would often sell various puzzle books and then also in the grocery store aisle, obviously you could buy puzzle books and you still can in the year.
Scott: But there's a certain aesthetic to those sorts of cheap printed puzzles.
Scott: Right.
Scott: We're like, you know, the ink isn't completely solid and is like speckled with like white dots in it.
Scott: because they didn't you know, they're not putting as much ink in the printing press and the art is very like repetitive.
Scott: Right.
Scott: There's just a certain feeling to it.
Scott: And so minimum minimum effort.
Scott: Yeah, so this website, Crazy Dad, has a bunch of puzzles on it of various kinds following that aesthetic.
Scott: Right.
Scott: They got your Sudoku's and Mazes and all kinds of stuff.
Scott: But one puzzle in particular, the haunted mirror maze puzzle, like really nails that aesthetic so hard of this was printed in some book.
Scott: that and your your kid has a whole book of them.
Scott: do it in the backseat of the car that you bought for like five bucks at a rest stop.
Scott: But it's also super cute with ghost vampires and zombies.
Scott: The vampire is also.
Scott: Oh, yeah.
Scott: And it's also a really interesting kind of puzzle.
Scott: It's obviously not like at the maximum puzzle level.
Scott: Right.
Scott: It's not super challenging, but it's you know, it's a little more challenging than it looks at first.
Scott: So it's sort of like a pea cross and where there's a grid and on the sides of the grid, it's telling you if you are standing at this point in the grid looking inwards, you will see this many bad guys.
Scott: Right.
Scott: Ghosts, vampires and zombies.
Scott: However, right, vampires, you can see if you're looking directly at them.
Scott: Right.
Scott: But you can't see them if they're reflected in a mirror.
Rym: Oh, that is way more complex than I thought it was going to be as I'm looking at this.
Scott: Right.
Scott: Ghosts, you can see, I think, is the opposite.
Scott: I think it's something like that.
Rym: Ghosts cannot be seen directly.
Scott: All right.
Scott: You can't see a ghost directly.
Scott: You can only see a ghost if there's a mirror reflecting.
Scott: Right.
Scott: And then a zombie is just a zombie.
Scott: You can just see it.
Scott: And so you have a grid and you have numbers and you have mirrors and you have.
Scott: so it says if you're standing here looking inwards, right, you could draw a path from the edge of the grid straight forward, bounce it off all the mirrors right until it hits the end.
Scott: And then you could say, well, if you follow that path, you can see five guys, five bad monsters.
Scott: Right.
Scott: And you have to basically put and it tells you on the grid there are two ghosts, five vampires, 10 zombies, however many.
Scott: And you have to place them in the grid correctly.
Scott: And there's only one legit way to place them.
Scott: that will work with all the different numbers in the side of the grid.
Scott: And it's pretty, pretty fun puzzle.
Scott: And you can just download just like a shit ton of.
Scott: he's got a hundred, a hundred books worth of them.
Rym: Yeah, the heart is a lot.
Rym: And they're they.
Rym: they're in vague order from book one to book one hundred.
Scott: It says the heart of each book has twenty four puzzles and there's one hundred books.
Scott: That's twenty four hundred puzzles in PDF format that you could just download.
Scott: They don't charge any money.
Scott: They just have PayPal donate links and you can donate if you want.
Scott: And they have a discord, I guess.
Rym: See, it's one thing, too, is like someone could theoretically have just written an algorithm to generate a lot of these.
Rym: But the fact that they are ranked by difficulty, that exponentially increases what I perceive to be the effort to make this good.
Scott: Yep.
Scott: And also the the artistic merit, even if you don't care about the puzzles.
Scott: Right.
Rym: Look at that vampire.
Scott: Yeah, I mean, in the artwork that's around the puzzles on the pages in the book, it's like these are these are puzzles that somebody, you know, did some amount of work on.
Rym: So in the meta moment, the geek night's book club book is did Scott update the website?
Rym: He did not.
Rym: It still says the murder.
Scott: I'm going to write that down right now.
Rym: But we're doing a walk on girl.
Rym: The book, since we talked about the anime movie quite some time ago on GeekNights.
Rym: Otherwise, we will be at Magfest doing a bunch of panels, very likely a PAX East doing at least one panel, maybe more.
Rym: And it is very hard to speculate on what else we might be up to beyond that particular time horizon.
Rym: Also can't say exactly how many episodes we'll do for the rest of this year, but December is looking OK, actually, in my calendar.
Rym: I think we got all our heavy lifting out already.
Rym: And in November.
Scott: Yeah, I mean, the only things I have on my calendar in December is basically, you know, I got one extra day off work because all the days off work are Mondays, which I already have off.
Scott: And, you know, one weekend doing holiday biz and hockey, I guess.
Scott: You know, it's not.
Scott: there's nothing really not until Magfest.
Scott: Right.
Scott: It's basically nothing.
Scott: Magfest, nothing, PAX East.
Scott: That's the current schedule.
Scott: No plans, really.
Rym: Plus, that hockey is warranting increasing attention due to the quality.
Scott: Very much so.
Rym: The quality that is being demonstrated, all the all the Rangers fans at my work have started to come out of the woodwork and talk about the team every goddamn day now.
Rym: Like people I didn't know were Rangers fans are just like talking about them all the time.
Scott: And, you know, the first of all, right, they're doing extremely well.
Scott: Yeah.
Scott: They're like the best points percentage.
Scott: They're not the most points, but they're the most points percentage of any team in the NHL, which basically means you're in first place.
Scott: You're the best team.
Scott: But they also have what?
Rym: Like the whole league.
Rym: They have like the third best power play.
Rym: They have an opportune penalty kill.
Scott: Right.
Scott: But also, you have to keep in mind that every other New York sports team has shit the bed.
Scott: Ah, that's the Mets and the Yankees didn't even make the complete garbage.
Scott: Right.
Scott: The Knicks, whatever the Nets, I've even heard from them.
Scott: I don't know what's happening over there.
Scott: The Giants, they got some story going on with Tommy Cutlets.
Scott: You know about the Tommy?
Rym: I don't know anything about what's going on with me.
Scott: Cutlets I got.
Scott: Well, it's very exciting, but I can't I'm not going to tell you now.
Scott: The point is, it doesn't matter what Tommy Cutlets does.
Scott: The Giants are so far out of a playoff spot.
Scott: There's no guarantee.
Rym: Oh, oh, oh, oh, I know what I know about this.
Rym: I know he's real good.
Rym: It's not going to help.
Scott: Kind of.
Scott: Not really.
Rym: According to it's more exciting.
Rym: Google that he is the passing paisan.
Scott: That is correct.
Scott: Then it's a fun story, but it's not a winning story.
Scott: Right.
Scott: So the Giants are going nowhere.
Scott: They can't.
Scott: they're done.
Scott: And the Jets obviously also have been done since the beginning of the season.
Scott: So there is literally no New York sports and Islanders are also, I guess, better than expected, but not good.
Scott: So it's it's all Rangers, the only New York sports team with anyone to do anything this this current time.
Rym: So so we did
Scott: see Hayao
Rym: Miyazaki's latest movie, The Boy and the Heron, or How Do You Live, which is it's kind of funny that, you know, in English, the title is The Boy and the Heron, considering that I found a note in the Wikipedia where the descendant of the author of the book, How Do You Live, express a perplexion at how the movie was tied to the book.
Scott: Yeah, I mean, I haven't read the book and Rym didn't choose the book for the book club, even though he could have.
Rym: I almost did.
Rym: It was it was it was a real hard choice.
Scott: Maybe I'll still read it.
Scott: Nothing stopping me from reading it, but I don't.
Scott: I haven't read it at this point.
Scott: But I am 100 percent sure, based on everything I know from every body and all the information available to me, that this movie does not actually bear much resemblance to that book.
Scott: Right.
Scott: There may be some thematic connection or, you know, it's not completely disconnected, but it is not an adaptation of the book.
Scott: the way that, you know, the Mr.
Scott: The North Star anime is an adaptation of the manga.
Rym: Yeah, it'd be like like GeekNights as adapted from Fist of the North Star.
Rym: Yeah, but we saw it.
Rym: It's a Miyazaki movie and there's a lot to unpack about it.
Rym: But I guess what I my main takeaway is that unlike a lot of other movies that I enjoyed a lot more and I'm not saying I didn't enjoy this movie, I actually did enjoy this movie.
Rym: This movie, even people who didn't like it, people who liked it, we all kind of kept talking about it.
Rym: Like it's come up in a lot of conversations.
Rym: So there's definitely something going on here.
Rym: And every time I spend more than a small amount of brain energy thinking about the movie, I think of more lit crit ideas about it, which means that he did something right.
Rym: But I also see a lot of people reacting extremely negatively to this movie for a lot of reasons that we can get into.
Scott: Well, I mean, I think in general is that you look at all the movies that Miyazaki has, you know, directed, been heavily involved in.
Scott: Right.
Scott: Not the ones that, you know, Studio Ghibli did that he wasn't so involved in.
Scott: Like a Whisper of the Heart or whatever.
Scott: And it's like basically, you know, he made basically everything on the list is like masterpiece, right?
Scott: It's like, you know, starting with Cagliostro, Naoshika, Laputa, Princess Mononoke, Totoro, Porco Rosso, I don't think I've even missed any.
Scott: Kiki and Spirited Away.
Scott: Right.
Scott: I don't think I've missed any.
Scott: Maybe I missed.
Scott: I don't know.
Rym: I don't think you have.
Scott: Right.
Scott: Those are the masterpieces.
Scott: And after Spirited Away was Howl's Moving Castle.
Scott: Now, was Howl's Moving Castle, you know, bad?
Scott: No, no, it wasn't bad.
Scott: But it wasn't.
Scott: It was the first one that wasn't a masterpiece in my at least as far as I say.
Rym: Right.
Rym: Because it was.
Rym: it was visually striking, thematically really good.
Rym: But the story kind of starts nowhere and goes.
Scott: It's hard to follow.
Scott: You can't really tell what's going on or why the characters are doing what they're doing or, you know.
Rym: And then it doesn't really end so much as it kind of just peters out and then the credits roll.
Scott: And then, you know, Ponyo similarly.
Scott: Right.
Scott: It's like, you know, what's actually the story here?
Scott: What's going on?
Scott: Right.
Scott: And so forth.
Scott: And I think, you know, in that sense, it's like the movies he's done since Spirited Away.
Scott: Right.
Scott: Have all, in my opinion, not been masterpieces the way the other ones were.
Scott: So he's basically set this ultra high bar for himself with a row of, you know, consecutive masterpieces that are all S tier.
Scott: Every single one.
Scott: Right.
Scott: Legendary.
Scott: And then kept going and has done, you know, not garbage.
Scott: Right.
Scott: Nothing bad.
Scott: You're not going to look at any of these that he was directing, at least.
Rym: Yeah.
Scott: And say, wow, that was terrible.
Scott: That's awful garbage.
Scott: F. Right.
Scott: Don't even want to look at that thing.
Scott: Would not watch if, you know, whatever.
Scott: Not never bad, but not masterpiece like he did before.
Scott: And so that's always disappointing.
Scott: Right.
Scott: And you still even now it's like, you know, I guess it took this long to where it's like, OK, I guess if he does another one, we have to keep the expectation and the not masterpiece zone.
Scott: Rather than rather than before where it's like, well, he hasn't done a masterpiece in several years, but I'm still holding out hope for one.
Scott: Let's go see the boy in the Heron.
Scott: Now it's like, OK, it's not going to be a masterpiece ever again.
Rym: Probably if it is, especially because there's something the boy in the Heron visually is is not one.
Rym: It does.
Scott: Oh, visually, it's just visually is.
Scott: Oh, yeah.
Scott: Yeah.
Rym: Well, because it does a thing on the same scale, like the same type of thing that Millennium Actors did, but in a very different way.
Rym: And it kind of goes through the styles of visual and thematic storytelling that his movies evoked over the years.
Rym: It's almost like Millennium Actors.
Rym: think through his own movies as Hayao Miyazaki, the creator.
Rym: So the tone and like the way it's like the animation is beautiful and shifts along.
Rym: But in terms of the core of what it's about and the core of the feelings you feel, the wind rises and the boy in the Heron are very similar in that they're very much.
Rym: Hayao Miyazaki is sitting there behind the screen, yelling, lit, crit and personal ideas at you via animation.
Scott: Right.
Scott: And there isn't you know, there are some characters that have, you know, strength.
Scott: And there are some, you know, powerful scenes here and there.
Scott: Right.
Scott: But, you know, like the Howl's Moving Castle, it's it's I guess Boy in the Heron is actually better to follow story wise than some of those other ones.
Rym: But I think the boy in the Heron actually is has a more intelligible plot than Howl's Moving Castle.
Scott: Very much so.
Scott: Yes.
Scott: But it's still not, you know, extremely tight.
Scott: Right.
Scott: It's still a little bit, you know, what's going on here?
Scott: A little bit.
Scott: Yeah.
Scott: Right.
Scott: It's like, why?
Scott: Why don't you tell me more about this?
Scott: I've evolved.
Scott: It's like, OK, I kind of get it, but that wasn't entirely clear or stuff just comes out of nowhere.
Rym: Yeah.
Rym: But upon further thought, like they all do kind of make sense.
Rym: But an example would be Emily saw the movie in a, I guess, twice an Academy Award screening before we saw it.
Rym: Yeah.
Rym: So Emily saw it and Emily was like, I'm not going to talk about it until you also see it, because I want to hear what you have to say about the fascist parakeets.
Rym: And I'm like, OK, I'm just going to wait to see what could be interpreted as a fascist parakeet.
Rym: And then in this movie, when there's the human sized parakeets carrying around Il Duce posters and literally enacting a fully fascist parakeet society about two midway through the movie.
Rym: Yeah, that was there.
Scott: That was close to the end of the movie.
Scott: That was like 75 to 80 percent of the way through the movie.
Rym: I think it was less than that.
Rym: I think it's more like maybe three fifths.
Scott: I don't know.
Scott: The parakeets don't appear until pretty late.
Scott: They appear pretty late.
Rym: There is a. there is a long segment that's probably longer than I remember of.
Rym: Are you going to kill the weird bird or not?
Scott: The bird, the parakeets show up pretty late in the film.
Rym: I have evolved through several interpretations of the fascist parakeets.
Scott: just by I mean, that's just because of who you are, that you're focusing so much on them.
Scott: And of course, yes, they are there.
Rym: Oh, no, but they're an example.
Rym: Every part of this movie.
Rym: I have a really big brain read about the scene where the dead Indiana Jones samurai style tries to go bust into the tower to save his son and the birds come out and he gets confused.
Rym: Like, I got thoughts about how that is specifically Miyazaki making a point about how the ideas that led to your work don't actually matter to the viewer.
Rym: The viewer sees what they see and interprets how they interpret it.
Rym: And the dad doesn't fucking understand what's going on in your tower.
Scott: Right.
Scott: So anyway, the overall structure of the movie is a very familiar formula that he's used before.
Scott: In most things.
Scott: And I've seen the formula used by other people as well, where a character goes to the underworld.
Scott: Well, I have a character who has a, you know, a human normal human world drama of some kind.
Scott: Right.
Scott: So in this case, there's a kid whose mom dies and his dad moves him out to, you know, a remote place out of the city and marries his mom's younger sister, basically.
Scott: So he has a family drama.
Rym: Right.
Rym: The child is understandably not taking it well in a way that very few people would, I think.
Scott: Yeah.
Scott: You know, and it's about, you know, all the feelings that the kid has in that situation.
Scott: Right.
Scott: And also the feelings that the, you know, the new mom has.
Scott: And, you know, the dad, he's just sort of like, I'm the dad.
Rym: Hello.
Rym: I'm a character in The Wind Rises.
Rym: I'm off not understanding why my son and wife are upset making fighter jets for or fighter planes for World War Two.
Rym: Yeah.
Scott: So the dad, his feelings aren't really a subject of the film at all.
Scott: Other than that, you know, kind of creepy.
Scott: Your wife died.
Scott: He just went married her younger sister.
Rym: That's kind of the dad.
Scott: So quick to like the situation within a year that.
Rym: Yeah.
Rym: But the dad not understanding the situation is definitely the point of the dad.
Rym: And Miyazaki did note that this is this is somewhat autobiographical about him having to flee with his family to the countryside as a child.
Rym: Yeah.
Scott: But anyway.
Scott: And so then what happens is that it's like, OK, you've created this this kid, he has this dramatic human real world situation, and then it's like, haha, we'll go on a series of adventure.
Scott: We'll go on an adventure into another world, another dimension, another somewhere, something.
Scott: Right.
Scott: And have a series of scenes, each dealing with something different.
Scott: And, you know, we're each has like a different message the same way that, like, you know, the Galaxy Express mom is killed.
Scott: Right.
Scott: I'll go on a train and there'll be a bunch of different scenes, a different planets.
Scott: And then at the end, right, wrap up back to the beginning.
Rym: The way you describe that, I think is really important because it's very telling about the parts of this movie that don't work well.
Rym: It does just feel like a whole bunch of set piece scenes that are connected by the thinnest thread.
Scott: Yeah.
Scott: You know, not on Galactic Railroad, you know, a train again, but, you know, the same thing where it's like has a problem, goes on the train, bunch of different things happen.
Scott: Right.
Scott: But also spirited away.
Scott: It's like, oh, you know, in the car with the parents.
Scott: Right.
Scott: Parents are turned into pigs, has to do a whole bunch of adventures with Dragon Boy.
Scott: And then back to the parents at the end, back to the human world, spirited away.
Rym: When you watch it, the like the scenes don't just hard cut between each other with these big gaps to see.
Rym: It feels like one long building.
Rym: And yes, there are exactly.
Rym: there are continuous momentum.
Scott: There's a logical reason.
Scott: Right.
Scott: And explanation for each sort of development into the next.
Scott: There are transitions in spirited away.
Scott: Right.
Scott: And there's also, you know, connections and other threads that sort of hold the thing together.
Scott: Tightly to where here, you know, it's like you're doing one thing and it's like what is holding it.
Scott: It's like, OK, you go into the next, you know, suddenly you're in this tower, but now you're in a boat place and there's totally different characters.
Rym: And it's like a pelican is going to give you a like Japanese kamikaze pilot soliloquy and then die in a scene.
Rym: And then that is never addressed again.
Rym: Yeah.
Scott: It's like, you know, what is how did we get from before to here?
Scott: It's like, you know, there was a thing that no one explained very well and it comes back, but it only comes back briefly and still isn't explained.
Scott: No, it's like.
Scott: it's like instead of a Chekhov's gun, that's like, yes, look at my Chekhov's gun, examine its shape and its size and let's just put it over here.
Scott: And then when it comes back, it comes back in a big way because that's how you tell stories.
Scott: Instead, it's like you saw Chekhov's gun at the corner of your eye and you couldn't quite get a good look at it.
Scott: And then a few scenes later, you see it again, but only briefly, and then you never see it again ever.
Scott: And it's like, did it fire?
Scott: Maybe it fired off in the distance.
Scott: And I heard like an echo of the gunshot.
Scott: It's like, it's like, hmm, you know, I noticed it.
Scott: It wasn't invisible, but like, it's not clear.
Scott: Yeah, I can't get a hold on it.
Rym: And I think we need to take a moment to like not knowing what it was about and then seeing the trailer that was only made for like the US because like Japan, there was no trailer.
Rym: It was just like in Japan.
Scott: I mean, in the story, there is a character who is who builds a tower and then writes a book while they're living in the tower and they die or disappear from the world.
Rym: Right.
Scott: They die slash disappear while leaving the book unfinished.
Scott: And it's like, yes, Miyazaki, we know that's what you've been trying to do for a long time now.
Scott: And the tobacco isn't working.
Scott: And so you somehow unluckily finished, I guess, this movie and we're left with no choice.
Scott: You couldn't make it even longer.
Scott: So you had no choice but to release it to the world.
Scott: And in Japan, everyone knows who you are.
Scott: So you don't need advertising or marketing.
Scott: You can just make a movie poster and nothing else.
Scott: Put it in the theater and everyone will come see it.
Scott: And in fact, you know, that may help you because if people see the trailer, maybe they'll be like, yeah, actually, that doesn't look good.
Rym: Well, the trailer looked pretty good, but here's what I'm getting at.
Rym: Emily also warned me because I was like, oh, yeah, the magic bird, the hair is a magic bird.
Rym: And then I was like, yeah, a cool magic bird.
Rym: Emily's like, it's not cool.
Scott: It's a little.
Scott: I wasn't expecting there to be like a literal heron or the heron to be a character.
Scott: I thought it would just be like, ah, yes, you know, the heron is a symbol and like maybe as a heron that flies past at an important scene.
Scott: It's like, no, the heron is a full on character that talks and is involved and is like, and let's just we got to be a huge supporting character, whatever you think the heron is going to be like.
Rym: No, it is not.
Rym: It is not.
Rym: I think that I think I'm going to use a phrase that I'm quoting a show that I don't think Scott watch gross and weird.
Scott: It is a gross and weird heron.
Rym: Indeed, it is a gross and weird heron.
Rym: It's really funny.
Rym: There's a scene early on like this is.
Rym: we're not going to spoil this movie, obviously, but there's a scene early on where like the heron clearly is like there's something up with it and it's trying to attract this kid's attention.
Rym: And then it escalates so fast from is the heron magical to the heron is like, hey, kid, you want to see a dead body and being creepy in the window?
Scott: Pretty much.
Rym: And it just gets worse and worse as the movie goes on.
Scott: Another creepy thing, I guess it's not creepy, but sort of an eww thing in this movie is that there's a lot of birds, not just the heron.
Scott: Right.
Rym: There's a lot of bird shit.
Scott: There's a lot of birds, but basically whenever birds appear, they start shitting all over everything like there is bird shit everywhere in this movie.
Rym: Where did I read this?
Rym: It was on like Verge or something.
Rym: There was an article, a long review of this movie that basically was only focused on the bird shit.
Scott: The main thesis was you couldn't I mean, it doesn't it's not like it's the whole movie just bird shit the movie, but it's to the point where you can't not notice it.
Scott: It is.
Scott: Yeah.
Rym: So the reviews premise was this was animated.
Rym: Every single pixel of bird shit was one hundred percent intentional, handcrafted for the viewer.
Scott: Correct.
Scott: Yes.
Rym: And there is so much more of it than you think there's going to be.
Scott: Oh, yes.
Scott: You can't not see it.
Rym: And there's definitely some allegory going on around the concept of a parakeet, you know, a parrot, perhaps parroting.
Rym: the work that they saw from the person that they worked for, but they don't understand its essence, almost like Mary and the Witch's Flower looked like a Ghibli movie or looked like a Miyazaki movie, but was bad.
Rym: Anyway, I think this movie takes a direct swipe at Mary and the Witch's Flower, but I digress.
Scott: I don't know.
Scott: I didn't really think of that when I was watching it.
Rym: I thought about that pretty early on and I feel pretty strongly about it.
Scott: OK.
Scott: But yeah, it's like, you know, should you go see it?
Scott: It's like, well, by the usual geek night standard of there is an anime movie in the theaters in the
Scott: U.S.,
Scott: right?
Rym: It's like, yeah, that's not a sequel.
Scott: You're not going to waste your.
Scott: it's not a sequel or an adaptation or just a faithful adaptation of anything, right?
Scott: It's like, you know, are you going to spend your money and be, you know, upset?
Scott: I guess maybe depending how much theaters cost where you are, but then you could just watch it for cheaper later when it comes out.
Scott: Right.
Scott: A streaming or pirating or whatever.
Scott: Just right.
Scott: You're not going to be upset about spending the time it takes to watch it.
Scott: At least I don't.
Scott: I wasn't.
Rym: But even that long.
Rym: It was two hours long.
Rym: Yeah.
Scott: But if you're expecting a Miyazaki masterpiece, don't don't expect that because that's not what you're going to get.
Rym: Expect something more.
Rym: like the wind rises and that you're going to leave and you're going to think, huh?
Rym: If you if you're the kind of person who likes lit crit, you're going to keep thinking, huh?
Rym: And if you don't like to do that kind of critical analysis of a film, I think that's the end of your thoughts about this.
Scott: I mean, the number one benefit, the positive thing you're going to get, obviously, is the stunning animation.
Scott: Right.
Scott: You know, he loves to do his, you know, sort of blobby, tentacle, you know, sort of liquidy animations that he sort of is like the liquid looks the water, the liquid, all that looks so good in this movie.
Rym: It stands out.
Scott: There was a scene where, like, they're on a boat and like some water gets in the boat and it's like you can see the water splashing around in the floor of the boat near their feet.
Scott: And it's like it's translucent.
Scott: And the lines in the in the wood are like refracting through the water when the water moves across.
Scott: And it's like someone, you know, for that thing that's in the corner, like you're supposed to be looking at the characters faces in that scene.
Scott: Right.
Rym: It's like someone I was looking at the water.
Scott: Yes.
Scott: Someone took the time to animate that water.
Scott: It's like, God damn.
Scott: Right.
Scott: It's like that's what they're doing that no one else is doing.
Scott: That's the primary reason to see the movie.
Scott: But secondly, there are, you know, some fun characters like the grandmas.
Scott: Right.
Rym: Oh, the grandmas are good.
Scott: Grandmas are real.
Rym: Also, there are, despite the movie's subject matter and everything we've said, there are several actual laugh out loud moments along the way.
Scott: It's a good comedy.
Scott: There's some.
Scott: there's some cute little white dudes, right.
Scott: So he's always got to have some cute sprite esque thing going on.
Scott: Only now they're white.
Rym: Yeah.
Rym: The scene with the hole in the beak might have been the funniest scene in the whole.
Scott: That was a funny one.
Scott: Yeah.
Scott: There's another thing, though, that I think is a positive for this movie, at least for me, is that I've noticed at least Shigeru Miyamoto and Miyazaki both expressing this particular feeling.
Scott: that is a feeling that I also had often in my life, particularly in my childhood, of there is some sort of hidden place or a hidey hole or a secret path in the woods or.
Scott: Right.
Scott: And it's like, you know, from Zelda one to, you know, most Miyazaki movies.
Scott: It's like here in this movie, the boy in the hair.
Scott: And it's, oh, there's a secret tower in the woods.
Scott: Right.
Scott: What's in there?
Scott: And it's like just that urge of, you know, like even in my life today, it's like I'll be walking around like a normal ass building and I'll see doors and I'm like, where's that door go?
Scott: What's behind that door?
Scott: I'll be like in the train station.
Scott: And there's like a door that's locked shut.
Scott: Right.
Scott: And it's clearly just maintenance shit behind the door and I still want to see.
Scott: And it's like, I got this urge, like, look at this light shining in.
Scott: So I'll peek.
Scott: It's like a hole in the door and I'll see the stuff that's in there and be like, oh, right.
Rym: And there's an Almanet concert when I discovered that we were, in fact, sitting on an elevator.
Scott: Right.
Scott: And it's just.
Scott: this movie is particularly good at evoking that same emotion, sort of nostalgic, explore the dark, small, hidden place, mysterious area feeling.
Scott: And if you want to feel that feeling, this movie is a good way to feel that feeling.
Rym: And so that's coupled with the main character moves to this house.
Rym: There's the creepy tower in the backyard.
Rym: The character does what any normal person would do and immediately checks it out because what the fuck is that?
Rym: That's right.
Rym: Like immediately.
Rym: And all the old people who live there are like, oh, yeah, that's the fucking tower where the guy disappeared.
Rym: We sealed it off because there's a bunch of drama that only made him want to go into the tower more.
Scott: Correct.
Rym: Like that is correct.
Rym: Good job.
Rym: And then and then and then the old lady's even like, oh, yeah, like your mom disappeared in that tower once for like a year and then came back and no one ever told you this.
Rym: Yeah.
Rym: What's that up to?
Rym: And then when the kid disappears, the dad immediately is like, oh, no, he's in the fucking tower.
Rym: Let's roll and like rolls up on the tower ready to storm.
Rym: Yeah, it's like there is zero ambiguity that the tower is real and that what happens inside of it literally happens.
Rym: This is not a was it all a dream kind of movie.
Scott: I do appreciate that also.
Scott: Right.
Scott: There's a lot of times, you know, there'll be a situation where it's like even, you know, Eska Flonie.
Scott: We'll be like at the very end.
Scott: It's like, you know, did it really happen?
Scott: Right.
Scott: Whereas here it's like it fucking happened.
Scott: Absolutely.
Scott: Everyone saw it.
Scott: No one was like, what?
Scott: You know, you're crazy talk.
Scott: What do you thought?
Scott: Everyone saw it.
Scott: Everyone believes it directly.
Rym: All the old people are like, oh, the family's fucking with that tower again.
Rym: Yeah.
Rym: I don't know why we warn him every time.
Scott: Yeah.
Scott: It's like, oh, there's the magic.
Scott: I've seen before.
Scott: Yep.
Rym: So, yeah, it's at some point.
Rym: I wouldn't be opposed to doing a more like critical analysis episode, but we'd have to just assume people have seen the movie because I do not have the energy to summarize the movie.
Scott: Yeah, I think I'd have to read the book at least first.
Scott: Right.
Rym: Just to see everything I'm reading implies that like nobody will see a significant connection between the two.
Scott: But you think that's the thing is I want to read it to be able to, you know, really see what is.
Scott: it isn't any.
Scott: there is a point in which in the movie the kid is reading a book and that book is titled How Do You Live?
Rym: Yeah.
Scott: So that's a little bit, you know, Lord of the Rings.
Scott: Right.
Rym: Or it could be never ending story.
Scott: There it's back again.
Rym: This has been GeekNights with Reman Scott.
Rym: Special thanks to DJ Pretzel for the opening theme.
Scott: Be sure to visit our website at FrontRowClue.com for show notes, discussion, links and more.
Rym: Remember, GeekNights is not one, but four different shows.
Rym: Mondays are science and technology, Tuesdays, gaming and games.
Rym: Wednesdays are animation and comics.
Rym: Thursdays are arbitrary and indiscriminate.
Rym: GeekNights is distributed under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 international license.
Scott: GeekNights is recorded live with no studio and no audience.
Scott: But unlike those other late shows, it's actually recorded at night.
Rym: And the Patreon patrons for this episode of GeekNights are Alan Joyce, Link Iggi, Dread Lily Tenderberry, Case of Care, Mix Music, Chris Haddad, Christopher Orr, Clinton Walton, Finn, Joel Hayes, Penny Grimer, Rebecca Dunn, Sam Erickson, Sherman Von Harland, a bunch of people who do not want me to say their names.
Rym: If you're one of the kind of person who listens to the stinger, then I urge you to write to the secretary of state in whatever state you live in, applauding Colorado's decision to remove Donald Trump from the ballot and encouraging them to defy the Supreme Court and remove him from the ballot regardless of anything.
Rym: Because you could point out to them, as some amicus briefs likely will in the near future, if a state were, let's say, in the United States to ignore the Supreme Court on the matter of whether or not someone is on the state ballot, the enforcement of that order would fall to the executive branch, which would be the current Democratic president, Joe Biden.
Rym: And if you can connect the dots, you can see how powerful that could be.
Rym: So start the grassroots now of expressing as a constituent of a state to the secretary of your respective state that you would support this and that you think it's a good idea.
Rym: And on that note, I leave you simply with.
Rym: you're not teching.
Rym: I'm trying to fast fall.
Rym: Well, you don't cancel fast enough.
Rym: Why is it so hard for me to do a short hop?
Scott: You're holding the button too long.
Scott: Just try flicking the side of it.
Rym: Oh, there it goes right there.
Scott: See?
Rym: Yeah, I think I was just hitting it too early.
Rym: Hey, what are you guys playing?
Scott: Val, you know exactly what we're playing.
Rym: Nah, the name totally slips my mind.
Rym: God, it was right on the tip of my tongue.
Rym: I had it a minute ago.
Rym: Just ignore him, slip.